But now, if we want to sum all the values in our original example,
ولكن الآن، إذا أردنا جمع كل القيم في مثالنا الأصلي،
we no longer need to write out all of the xs.
فلن نعد بحاجة إلى كتابة جميع xs.
Instead, we can write our summation starting at i=1 and ending at the fifth value.
بدلاً من ذلك، يمكننا كتابة تجميعنا بدءًا من i=1 وينتهي بالقيمة الخامسة.
This is way better when wanting to extend to 10 or 20 or even 100 values.
وهذه طريقة أفضل عند الرغبة في التمديد إلى 10 أو 20 أو حتى 100 قيمة.
We no longer need to write out all of those xs.
فلن نعد بحاجة إلى كتابة جميع xs هذه.
However, we can be even more efficient than this.
ومع ذلك، يمكننا أن نكون أكثر كفاءة من ذلك.
Each time our data set changes,
في كل مرة تتغير فيها مجموعة البيانات،
I have to change this number at the top to indicate how many values I'm summing.
يجب تغيير هذا الرقم الموجود في الجزء العلوي للإشارة إلى عدد القيم التي أقوم بتجميعها.
If we really just want to sum all of our values,
إذا أردنا حقاً جمع كل قيمنا،
we can replace this top value with n. Now our notation will work for any data set.
فإنه يمكننا استبدال هذه القيمة العليا بـ n.الآن سوف يعمل الترميز الخاص بنا لأي مجموعة بيانات.
So far, we have a way to sum all of
حتى الآن ، لدينا طريقة لتجميع جميع
our values regardless of how many are in our data set.
قيمنا بغض النظر عن عددها في مجموعة البيانات الخاصة بنا.
In order to finish this calculation of the mean,
لإنهاء هذا الحساب للمتوسط،
we need to divide our sum by how many values are in our data set.
نحتاج إلى تقسيم المجموع على عدد القيم الموجودة في مجموعة البيانات الخاصة بنا.
But this is just n. You would commonly see the mean of the data set notated like this,
ولكن هذا مجرد n. من الشائع أن ترى متوسط مجموعة البيانات التي تم ذكرها مثل هذا،
which we pronounce as x-bar,
والذي ننطقه مثل x-bar،
and it is calculated with this notation which says you sum
ويتم حسابه باستخدام هذا الترميز الذي يوضح أنك تجمع كل القيم
all of the values in the data set and then
في مجموعة البيانات ثم تقسمها
divide by the number of values in the data set.
على عدد القيم في مجموعة البيانات.
Learning notation can be tough.
يمكن أن يكون تعلم الترميز أمرًا صعبًا.
Don't be afraid to watch this video more than once.
لا تخف من مشاهدة هذا الفيديو أكثر من مرة.
Before we move on to the next sections,
قبل أن ننتقل إلى الأقسام التالية،
there are quizzes available in the next module to
تتوفر مجموعة اختبارات في الوحدة التالية
assure you've mastered the concepts we've introduced here.
للتأكد من أنك قد أتقنت المفاهيم التي عرضناها هنا.